So, needless to say, the American
Revolution was kind of a big deal. But,
one of the biggest effects of that big
revolutionary deal was the development
of a more distinct American identity,
and I reckon we ought to talk about
that. So, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, now before we get cozy with the
features of this burgeoning American
identity during the post-revolutionary
period, I need to tell you something
very important. Like, if you see a
question or an essay prompt about
American identity on an exam and you do
not remember what I'm about to say, then
you're burnt. Okay, here it is. After
the Revolution, a new national American
identity showed signs of development.
However, it is of vital importance to
remember that regional cultures and
identities were still very strong. Like,
if you're watching this and you're an
American, then you've grown up in a time
when you probably identify as an
American first and not necessarily as a
Georgian or a Michigander or whatever.
Oh, and by the way, if you want to know
guys to follow along with this video and
all my videos, then check that link in
the description. Anyway, that's not how
it was in the era that we are
considering. In general, Americans of
that age were far more attached to their
regional identity than they were to
their national identity. it's true that
movements like the First Great Awakening
worked to create a more common identity
among the colonists that had existed
before, it still regional identity won
out. However, the American Revolution
itself was a major event that created
the conditions for an even stronger
national identity than even the Great
Awakening. But, even still, you need to
remember that Americans of that age
still had kind of a layered identity
with national and regional layers, you
know, like a juicy lasagna or one might
say an ogre. Ogres have layers. Okay, so
with that big idea hanging as a banner
over the rest of our discussion, then
let's talk about the development of a
national culture in the United States
and contrast it with the regional
variation. Now, perhaps more than
anything else, American identity in this
period coalesced around the idea of
liberty. The Constitution begins with
the words "We the people," and then the
chief characteristic of that we was that
they possessed the blessings of liberty.
Therefore, one of the key features of
the emerging national identity after the
Revolution was that Americans were a
free people. And I'll give you two
illustrations that demonstrate how that
identity was beginning to work itself
out. First was the abolishment of
aristocracy. Now, if you recall from my
video on the Constitution, in the
aftermath of the Revolution, every state
adopted a new constitution. And every
dang one of them mandated that their
governments existed by the consent of
the governed that no titles of nobility
or hereditary aristocracy would be
allowed. Now, this, of course, was a
reaction against the way social power
was held in Europe, not least in Great
Britain. There, power was passed down
through families, which is to say, it
was hereditary or inherited. So, all
that mattered with respect to who wore
the social power pants was that that
person was born into the right family,
not whether or not they were actually
skilled in the wise use of power.
Therefore, by abolishing the social
hierarchy of hereditary power, Americans
embraced the idea of meritocracy. And
that just means that any person could
work their way up through the ranks of
the social ladder owing to their talent
and not necessarily their family of
birth. And that whole idea was linked to
a growing emphasis on more widespread
education because an educated population
was the only way to maintain the civic
virtue that a meritocracy demanded. And
here's where I tell you that there were,
of course, regional variations on this
whole liberty element of national
identity. I probably don't have to tell
you by now that the idea of meritocracy
and opportunity for all patently did not
extend to all Americans. First of all,
let's talk about women. Now, despite the
significant movements for the
democratization of politics in the new
states, many of which at least lowered
property requirements for voting, women
were apparently not deemed worthy of the
promises of liberty. For example, women
had no legal standing in the states and
were instead understood as dependents of
their fathers or husbands, and in that
way, the men represented women
politically. Therefore, in all the
states, women were encouraged to
participate politically not by voting,
but by raising and educating virtuous
sons who could then shape the future of
the nation. And if you recall, this was
known as the Republican motherhood. But
then, perhaps the most significant
regional variation on the theme of
liberty was the presence of slavery.
Now, some states in the north moved
toward the emancipation of enslaved
blacks. For example, Vermont's
constitution banned slavery immediately,
while Pennsylvania's made provisions for
a gradual emancipation. And all northern
states introduced some form of abolition
by 1804. But, southern states were in no
mood to interpret the principle of
liberty thusly. That's because they
relied heavily on enslaved labor for the
success of plantation agriculture and
therefore allowed
to remain entrenched in their society,
effectively cutting off all hope of
America's black population to enjoy the
blessings of liberty. And that's a
pretty massive bummer, but you
definitely need to know that the black
population of America didn't just sigh
and go on with their lives as second or
third class citizens. No, in many ways,
they worked to form their own notions of
American identity. For example, our boy
Gowan Pamphlet was formerly enslaved,
but then gained his freedom. And after
doing so, he became a minister and led
one of America's earliest black Baptist
congregation. And in that way, he was
able to demonstrate how marginalized
voices could still claim their portion
of the American identity lasagna even
when the rest of society was not yet
ready to deliver on its promises.
Additionally, free blacks in the north
established mutual aid societies, church
communities, and various educational
institutions to work for the betterment
of their own people, and all of this in
spite of their ongoing social and legal
marginalization. Okay, now this second
illustration of the emergence of a
national identity concerns religious
toleration. Now, during the colonial
period, many colonists were suspicious
of the entanglement of church and state,
not least because the British used the
Anglican Church as an instrument of
control in the colonies. But, after the
Revolution, most of the states erected a
wall of separation between church and
state. And as a result, most of the new
states completely defunded their state
churches in order to keep private
matters like religion free from
government meddling. But again, there
were significant regional variations on
this theme of religious toleration. For
example, Massachusetts mandated church
attendance in its constitution, while
also emphasizing freedom of worship,
which shows a deep commitment to its
history with the Congregational Church.
Okay, now let's finish by doing a quick
survey of how American national identity
was showing up in art and literature and
architecture. Now, as far as artists
were concerned, let me introduce you to
two of them. First was Charles Willson
Peale, who painted Revolutionary War
leaders like Washington and Franklin and
Jefferson as Republican heroes. Now,
Peale mainly adopted the Neoclassical
style, which emphasized order and
harmony, and thus his portraits
romanticized the subjects and events
that he portrayed. And in that way, they
contributed to the emerging national
identity by glorifying the heroes and
events of the Revolution. I mean, look
at Peale's most famous portrait titled
Washington at Princeton. The lighting is
really dramatic, and Washington looks
like a straight-up boss. And you know,
if you don't respect him, he's going to
blow you up with a cannon. Anyway, the
second artist to know is John Trumbull.
Like Peale, he also painted historical
scenes from the Revolution in the
Neoclassical style, the most famous of
which was the signing of the Declaration
of Independence. Now, Trumbull's
depictions were also real drippy and
romantic. Like, the serenity of his
depiction of this event was entirely
fictional. It was way more chaotic, and
most of those people were never even
there at the same time. But, in
romanticizing the signing of this
document, Trumbull helped Americans
identify with this moment as a key
ingredient in what it meant to be an
American. Okay, in terms of literature
as evidence of American identity, let me
tell you about Hector St. John de
Crèvecoeur. And this guy was considered
to be one of the first, if not the
first, truly American novelist. book,
Letters from an American Farmer, he
described the American as a new man that
blended European roots with frontier
opportunity. Additionally, he described
America as a land of opportunity and
social mobility on account of its
devotion to the principles of liberty,
while also noting the dark realities of
slavery. And finally, let's consider how
architecture contributed to an American
identity. So, starting in 1792,
construction began on the US Capitol in
northern Virginia. Now, it was
constructed in the Federal style of
architecture, which was an explicitly
American mashup of the Neoclassical
style inspired by Greek and Roman
architecture. this style, with its domes
and columns and symmetry, emphasized
order and democracy. And more to the
point, this was a deliberate shift from
the Georgian style of architecture,
which was popular in the colonial
period, and that signaled a deliberate
break from British culture. Well, okay,
you can click here to watch my other
Unit 3 videos, or you can click here to
grab my video note guys, which is going
to help you cram all the contents of
this course firmly into your brain fold.
I'm glad you came around, and I'll catch
you on the flip-flop. I'm Lorout.